so in
the in relation to what we've been
saying last few talks regarding the Mind
wild animal the simil what would the
gratification of sensuality
be can you have internal resistance
without cality
cality
yes so then it's not quite the beginning
cality it's yeah it's the proximate
cause more often than not and people
want to avoid paying it to sensuality
but just within sensuality where is its
origin where is
that
gratification what is the gratification
we still have an answer that sayic
Delight so the the the Zeal the Delight
towards towards the pleasure towards the
pleasure yeah towards the prospect of
pleasure but even that it's like the
thing that makes it Pleasant is the
Delight not the kind of idea of pleasure
that's yeah exactly the Delight is
already it's gratification that's the
point are you asking in terms of the
simil in terms of the animal in terms of
the whole thing everything the mind you
whatever you be
saying mind can see only Only You
pressures you to things he wants through
you you are its puppet
basically you know the five strings they
called strings CU they control you like
a puppet like a puppeteer controls a a
doll so
uh and yes you know you're you're acting
towards pleasure cuz you want to avoid
pain you want to avoid pressure you want
to avoid the resistance but all of that
kind of secondary to
the origin of that
gratification that
Delight so where is that
light but I'm just asking so from the
point of you of if you
imagine or recollect a sensual desire of
any kind Titan SM this touches there is
pressure there is
craving even before you engage with the
objects the gratification is there
through the presence of the
light where does that Del light come
from come mind which one which
mind your mind or the animal mind the
animal's mind that's where it's like
a
Untamed in kind of so the joy towards
uality comes from the animal that's what
you're saying yes anybody
else that's what I that's what I
would yes that's what I but I want to
check it does it does that's the whole
point and that's why you could be
telling yourself all you
want that sensuality of his little
satisfaction and all this when the Mind
wants it you see no escape from that you are
it you see no escape from that you are
under there that's why the only way to
begin that sort of
U to begin liberating yourself from it
is through sense restraint first simply
to not give in towards what CH wants you
to do wants to use you as a puppet
basically to to
experience things through you because it
only can see it can only see you and
um and that's um so for as long as you
don't basically if you would not have
discerned a mind for what it is you
can't even see the origin of of
gratification so your your efforts
toward sensuality would well would not
be uprooting
it you would not be um addressing the
the the the problem for what it is which
is no no no you need to convey to the
mind that it's actually better to not
want it for itself not for
you and because it is fact better to not
want it it is a burning amember even for
the wild animal it can then get you know
it can it can get that message if you if
you uh if you're able to communicate to
it and that's then when you go beyond
sensuality I when your own animal is not
pressuring you towards it anymore not
when you chose to do so or
something and that's why the Buddha
would say in the sutas like even he
would in the beginning when he would be
like he so I I saw the extent how
unsatisfactory sensuality is how little
Joy it provides how more Peril yet still
my mind would not leap towards that he
would still not want it and then I
thought priation
yeah it's like and it's like oh why why
is that the case oh because it hasn't so
he hasn't communicated the danger of it
to the Mind well enough and when it did
then the Mind started preferring as well
not going into
sensuality but people often think well
normally obviously what else can they
think cuz you you don't start by seeing
the mind you don't start by Discerning
that space in between as a phenomena
really such peripherally known um then
you just think okay I have this desire
but at the same time I don't want it I
see how bad it is but I can't help it
but then I do it then I can't stop doing
it then I stop doing it then I start
doing it again and it's just this
constant sort of turmoil and internal
conflict of well seemingly wanting it
and not wanting it at the same
time but it's you could well not be
wanting it through and through as far as
you are concerned but that's not where
the power comes from comes from the fact
that the wild animal that is still
invisible to you wants it and you don't
even see the animal so how can you then
talk to it how can you then get the
timing right to to convey the message
and so
on so how do you then convey to your
mind that the renunciation is good for
it
well you have to start by kind of
renouncing physically taking it out of
100% well you won't even see your mind
if you don't cuz I think I think we said
that we must said that in the previous
Talks Like You Don't See Your Mind by
somehow directing your attention to the
neither here nor there in between you
see it by withdrawing the threshold of
your perception from the sense objects
not I through sense restraint through
not fueling desire and last for those
objects anymore you you get to then see
the internal counterparts and so on not
because you chose
to so say somebody is obviously seeing
their the mind which means they would
have been established in
virtue they're not approaching it
through some sort of sensation watching
in the area of their
heart which obviously won't be the mind
um so how would they then
start conveying the message
that denunciation is what the mind also
actually wants even when it goes
toity so we went through the like list
last talk of which one of like yeah
physical verbal and then yeah yeah sense
restraints Andra okay thoughts the
images like but you also now like in in
in this uh um in this example of
specifically when it comes to
sensuality you want
to present it with certain contexts
because the mind needs to see it for
itself the dog needs to get the message
not just emulate your
behavior of course without emulating
your behavior there will be no message
but what's the message correct
contemplation so like the Mind sees you
you can choose what you choose to like
how you choose to attend to things as in
so you the way you attend to things will
kind of in you know you you the way you
attend yeah but does it also matter what
you attend well exactly that's what I
mean like the way you attend they kind
of go together in this in this
particular instance because obviously
you can't do like the correct
contemplation of of the danger of
sensuality without having a certain way of
without having a certain way of
attending to that danger as well
yeah well that's that's what the S would
say as well like whatever one frequently
thinks and Ponders that's what his mind
starts to Incline
towards so you realize oh yeah so the
dog hates renunciation doesn't want to
hear about it but obviously I'm the one
chained it I'm the one responsible for
training it so I'll just keep presenting
this context to it but that's now that
part of how you attend to it so you
could just go into like Mindless body
contemplation as the traditional way of
um body parts would think it's done but
no no no you got to actually present it
with the factual danger that will be
felt so it needs to be like a living
contemplation not just just going
through the mental motions of of images
of body parts and stuff no it's like no
no no there is an actual danger in this
you need to you need to feel the danger
you need to recognize the bait or there
is poison in that thing that you want to
eat right there o thank you that was so
close if you didn't tell me I would have
consumed it that's the only way for the
mind to get the message across no amount
of just you know teacher student
government curriculum information
passed yes this suta says that and that
suta says this and there is 32 parts and
there's 16 ways of going about it and
there you go you have finished your
contemplation of the
auba it's like no no them mind has to
feel that and then that's you keep doing that
that and then that's you keep doing that
for as long as the Mind still inclines
towards it until actually you realize and you
it until actually you realize and you
would know because the
mind well if the Mind still inclines
towards it or if not that becomes your
feedback exactly that's it so it's like
oh look I can stop now cuz it's not
actually trying to go to that he doesn't
want it anymore he genuinely
wants to have nothing to do with it
and then you protect it in that state
you don't get careless and start
presenting it cuz see each time you
choose
to look smell taste Touch Hair
unsuitable S sound smell taste
touch it's unsuitable for the mind as I
said before you can well handle it it
doesn't do anything to me but is that
animal fully completely utterly 100 100%
trained without any underlying
Tendencies left in
it or it's not and you know the answer
already so if it's not these things are
unsuitable for it although you're fine
nobody denies that you the greatest the
most restrained person can hold
everything in the world but the mind
that's not developed can't so in the
same sense you will be presenting it
with the right context of danger and how
little satisfaction and so on well
through simply choosing to look smell
taste touch um unsuitable smell s on
smell taste touches you are now giving
it the opposite context well I mean yeah
now you're giving it the context of oh
look this this this good thing again
that I always
wanted basically you've always been
training it for something EXA there is
no neutral yeah so it's either suitable
or unsuitable beneficial or unb
beneficial so it's to recognize that cuz
sometimes people is like and that's
exactly how people would like go against
the precepts or sensor strange oh I can
it's not a
problem for me and it's factually
true probably more often than not it's
like oh it's not a problem for me but
it's like oh yeah but the mind will get
the wrong message if I look at these
things T taste these things and when I
say unsuitable sight sound smell taste
touches it means done through that
intention of distraction
sensuality uh you know what type they
are and uh that will automatically be
sending a message to the mind even if
you say I'll do it quietly so you won't
see it it is you doing it you wouldn't
be doing it if it weren't for that well
exactly exactly once you don't do it
then you realize oh the mind it was
basically already there was an
underlying pressure from the mind come
on come on just this
once so if you you
can aware of the Mind leaning in a
certain direction
wants to okay the eye you know wants to
look somewhere wants to turn something and
somewhere wants to turn something and
you know you can feel that that he wants
to do
that and uh so you start noticing the
ugly aspects of the
situation while it's trying to look at
the beautiful well no you have to see the
beautiful well no you have to see the
animal first in order to present the
context yeah that's what I mean like if
you see it leaning in a specific
Direction that's what I mean right right
right so then when you when you're
thinking of the uh asuba context you're
not thinking it to cancel your own
thoughts you're thinking it just to
broaden the context for theal I don't
know it's kind of obvious where leaning
you get the flavor of where it's leaning
that direction yeah and then you bring
up whatever other ugly context sure sure
sure if it's done for the mind that it's
being seen peripherally yeah not not if
it's not if it's done just as a as a
response to oh I must think the
opposite I'm just clarifying that
whoever listens to this does not jump to
conclusion of oh I must think the
opposite every time something present
itself no no no yeah I'm wondering if
it's not a
response because the mind is leaning in
Direction you could say it is a form of
response you are responding I'm not
trying to deny that exactly but is your
response rooted in trying to deny the
whole thing it's unpleasant or is your
response yes yes there is this beautiful
that's what you want okay I understand
and this is what comes with it and then
you present everything else on top of
that thing not
instead yeah together and then it's like
oh it's like that Su where
anyway that I translated as the seeing
the other side so the bigger picture
other half of the picture so it's not
about denying the one side as but and then
denying the one side as but and then
just focusing on the ugly yeah no no
that's absolutely fine it's just that
obviously can sound the
same to somebody who is not even seeing
the mind and that's really the point see
like when you're trying to deny things
you're aiming that denial at the mind at
the whole pressure at everything so
there's no communication it's just
denial of everything so and that's how
people do a subba that's how people do
loveing kindness I just just want to
replace the whole thing well it's going
to be done in the wrong time
well exactly well the whole thing is
already wrong yeah so the mind is still
getting the message of aversion through
it so now it's going to be even more
ofers so next time you're going to have
even more
hate um so or you keep presenting a
subba trying to just blindly not teach
the mind to not want it but just blindly
cancel it he learned to love that and he
get attracted to a subba now cuz you're
presenting it on top of its own existing
undiminished delight and desire it's
going to start seeing beautiful in that
as it happened so many times in the
suas and that's that's already the
difference between you are you just
justifying your attempts and
managing the the Arison discomforts or
are you really trying to approv
them because you yeah this is
uncomfortable this pressure but it's
like okay so I could just try and deny
the whole thing and distract myself from
it basically in the process of doing so
so I don't have to deal with it or I
could like really address the root cuse
which is the the the animal delighting
in things it shouldn't and I'm being
pressured on account of it and I'm being
controlled and pushed and so on like a
puppet and for that it takes a bit more
Nuance than just okay just think the
opposite thoughts it's like no you have
to
discern well first you have to stop
trying to get rid of the pressure cuz
then you won't discern the pressure you
can't discern the extent of the pressure
cuz by Discerning the extent of the
pressure you discern the extent of the
mind so now while the pressure is there
you feed the right context to it you
present it and even if he doesn't want
it you keep them there while the
pressure is there that's the training
that's the enduring on the right level
as he keeps
saying that's the right level pressure
cannot be aced out shouldn't be acted
out of this is the whole picture that you're
of this is the whole picture that you're
ignoring why are you pressuring me same
imagine a little spoiled
brat cries and screams to get what he
wants and it's it's it's causing a scene
publicly and you're feeling eyes of
everybody on you because of what your
unruly kid is
doing oh you could give give me so it
stops but then you just you just convey
the message to that kid okay next time I
want something I'll do exactly the same
thing and I'll get what I want
but if you don't give into that pressure
it's going to feel
uncomfortable but then the kid will get
the right message okay this does not
work and then it will stop trying that's
the point you can't reason with it because
point you can't reason with it because
it doesn't it doesn't think like that it
doesn't think on that level but you
could indicate the benefits and the
non-benefits of that behavior and then
it can feel that for itself
so you know that talut the poet the
verses that he was wri to his mind you
could read that poetically like you know
he's like a poet talking to his own mind
but you could also understand it
phenologically like he was actually
addressing his mind the phenomenon of
his mind that he very much clearly seen
and understood and he was saying like oh
understood and he was saying like oh
before when he was a householder he was
romanticizing about you know committing
his life to the practice and living in
the mossy forests with deers and streams
in the mountains where no people go and
practice in seclusion and complete his
training and so on but now when he is
living in the forest with moss and
streams and mountains and the deer comes
and so on and no people go the Mind
wants to go back to the central
life so I was like no now you're going
to stay here you brought me here now I'm
going to keep you
here until you get used to this and
start to like it and want it Whatever It
Takes how long it takes doesn't matter
and then it did and then he became out
hand so because the Delight comes from
the animal that's why you need to teach you
animal that's why you need to teach you
the danger of
it you're not I already know the danger
I don't to think about it it's not about
you it's about getting through that
getting that message through to the to
the animal like until it actually sees
oh
yes and then the Escape becomes obvious
what would be the
Escape no one thing for both of you
exactly complete absence of any trace of
delight coming from the animal and we
are both
freed so like the animal's winding
itself wants to wind myself up say with
thoughts of complaining about whatever
just want it wants to Delight in the
thoughts about about complaining about
others or whatever mhm and you can see
that is discerned and okay well don't do
that just don't go in that
direction well we won't be going there
um you know you won't be you you don't
let it out but it wants to yeah and then
so it calms down because you have you've
put that boundary for it yeah and it
calms down and then you note whatever it
is after some period of time see is this
better fact better
yeah yeah and that's where the
recognition would come see that's like
why so many times it said in the sutas
but obviously it's so easy to over read
like virtue results in
Sami nothing else results in Sami no
like no concentrating and focusing could
result in composing the wild animal Mak
makes no difference to it well in fact
actually makes a negative difference to
it because you're focusing more on the
objects of your
senses but it's the virtue that calms
down the animal The Virtue calms down
the Mind established in virtue leads to
Sam the the the whole the relay chariots
we did before
so exactly not acting out of the UN
wholesome pressures calms the
mind until the
recognition discernment would then occur
as a result of it oh see this is
factually better isn't it and then the
mind would see it oh yes it is and then
you keep repeating that for as long as
there Tendencies comes up again again
remember this so the
so the
Delight is the gratification the
gratification the
danger what's the
danger was the most immediate
danger the stent have talk about it in
different ways depending obviously I
think on the audience sometimes the
danger is that well if you want
sensuality you have to go and plow
fields and endure elements and work work
hard in in Ure lots of
discomfort but what's the more immediate
what's the most immediate
danger of giving it soci
suffering well yeah that's OB the true
but also
Delight but from the point of view of
like that the liability to just being
under that pressure because Delight is
already pressuring it's well yeah the
Delight is a pressuring but you can
handle the pressure most people can to
some
extent but what's the actual you know
the danger The Chopping Block the death
all the similar that would have gave
when it came to sensuality it's a bit
more than just the
pressure pressure is the the Gateway for
the communication and everything else
contact is the Gateway but but what is
that danger that you want to convey to the
mind that it can see for itself then and
stop doing
it so if the Delight comes from the
animal does the danger come from the
animal as
well the completely wild
Untamed thing that you are you're
attached to but you have no control that
is your puppet but more specifically how
does that manifest how does that wild
uname nature would manifest so that you
realize oh that is actually the
pedal the heart of
it how do you scare that child to its
core so it never does that ever again
the extent of its capacity to Delight is
the extent of its capacity
to bite itself to bite you yeah yeah
yeah it's so as I said
it's so as I said
before the the immediate danger is
liability you being liable to that
animal just to turn against you at any
given second
but what's in it for the animal so
that's the danger that's apparent to you
but you want also animal to see that as
unbeneficial for
itself whether it's you know Pleasant
unpleasant neutral whatever kind of
suffering is there is because of craving
because of the and that's it so like
when it's so it when there's sensual
craving like the well yes and I see
where you're getting it the craving is
bad fundamentally you're better off
without it but the
gratification the danger and the Escape
are specifically need to be seen in the
specific contexts of sensuality of
anything you depend
on so these are the specific messages
that need to be conveyed to the
mind yes craving is bad it would be much
like everybody would be better off
without it but the mind doesn't
understand that so you show it the
Delight that he comes from it there is
gratuitous and it will stop Delight it
if you show it the danger of its own
Delight so the danger for you obviously
your interest there is to tame the
animal so it doesn't bite your face off
but what's in it for the animal why is
it beneficial for the animal to not just
bite your face off
it's wildness is factually unpleasant
that's what I that's what I'm trying to
say it's fact it's it's it's well it's
factually pleasant but animal doesn't
see the facts because that's the point
like if you're wild you don't see that
as a
problem you need to scare it to see
there's a problem there slightly
indirect everything is indirect there is
no
the like less immediate than that or
that you're talking about there's no end
I mean this this is how I would describe
it this like in that direction it's
just there's no hope for again like
imagine a crazed drug addict exactly
they don't have a re they I know it's
unpleasant I don't care I will still
kill you cuz you in my way yeah exactly
so how do you then a person who is not
reasonable an animal that follows no
reason or
facts how do you scare it to stop doing
it
so it's a drug yeah so he wants the drug
and he's desperately once he's in the
he's desperately once he's in the
craving
mode that's my point Whenever there is a
delight there is no reason to that
extent so you're presenting the the the
right context but
fundamentally in order to get through to
the danger becomes apparent it needs to
sink in through the animal as well that
it's dangerous
so I'm asking for you it's going to be
oh this thing at any given second can
turn against me that is the most
immediate danger you're you're presenting the
danger you're you're presenting the
context of
like disagreeability discuss in things
that he wants so he loses the desire but
fundamentally the Escape comes from
really recognizing the danger of even
the slightest giving into that the
slightest wanting of the animal so
that's what I'm asking like is it like
you're asking about the danger not of
giving into it that's already like kind
of secondary the danger is not about
like the danger Delight it's the danger
of delighting yes that's that's the
danger graic gratification danger and
the Escape you you recognize the
gratification is the Delight what's the
danger of
it
well the non Escape H the
non it's more than that well you're
describing isn't it then you would be in
the context of relative calm in the
sense that you're not acting out like
you've already done the you've already
put the boundaries around that's done so
it's already in a state of relative of
course and so so because you wouldn't be
seeing the animal to begin with so
that's all covered we don't need to re
you're delighting in death what is
subject to what is death like you're to
the extent of the Delight you're you're
you're going to die basically to the
extent of delight that's the extent of
death of basically being subject to
death self-destruction self-destruction
yeah yeah that's the message you want to
correct convey to it because that's the
message you get from it that's the point
when you recognize that the animal can
attack you at any given time you
realize like at any given time
regardless of the circumstances
regardless this thing from the
inside can just end
me and you realize oh there is nothing
in the world that can come in between
that and that's obviously the would be
the scariest feeling If you experience
it on account of virtue and sense
restraint which you probably will at
some point you can contain it because
you realize well as long as I don't act
out of this it's contained but you would
have to see at least some extent of it
or that is the
danger but it's not the danger because
you're paired with the mind it's not
going to kill you just because you're
paired with it will kill you because
it's wild while you're paired with
it so you realize any trace of delight
that I would tolerate or allow or Not
address is the direct link to this
murderous thing that's inside of
me like there's nothing that can come in
between and then you realize well that
in and of itself it's the end of the
animal yeah so it will act for it own
harm if he does
that so animal
delighting in sensuality means animal
delighting in its own absolute demise
and it doesn't want to end why would
it but you need to make that connection
for it Delight means the demise not oh if I
it Delight means the demise not oh if I
give into this and then this and then
this then the the danger of sensuality
comes and becomes apparent no no no
you'll already acting out the pressure
of sensual Delight you're not seeing the
animal you're not addressing the Delight
that comes from the
animal the hidden murderer with a that
unpredictable intent it's there because
of that you remove the Delight you're
the best
friend nothing can cause you to suffer
ever
again how do you remove the light well
as we've just been described
you keep presenting this context to it
and whenever you even recognize so you
have to keep a watchful eye on the space
in between quote
unquote so by putting
back the choice by making the choice
clear to the animal that's how I can
stop doing
it by connecting by associating well
choice of delight means choice of this
and it's like okay thank you
so that's why it's like initially it's
like the scariest thing but there is a
Liberation hiding in
it CU it's like oh the
murderous intimate friend how to say
it's like but only because of the
Delight only because of the craving not
because of its own ficity or something
so if I convey the message that that
intent that that that craving and
Delight is killing itself as well it
will stop doing it and I'll be free as a
result of
it cuz that's what I was saying I think
in that talk the danger is that the Mind
turns against
itself in that
fit of pressure or whatever it's just
obviously people would not even come
near here seeing
that because they would not have been
they were not withdrawn from sensuality
and distractions sufficiently
enough so as I said you can be living
with a wild dog but you're
constantly feeding it treats and
constantly uh occupy its attention with
activities he won't turn and look at you
in a sense of like you're a stranger why
are you doing in my territory I don't
want you here but if you start saying
not to your distractions and stuff
that's the first thing you is going to
become apparent that's I said before
like people start panicking just because
you know they stop watching TV and
listening to news they panic attacks and
whatnot because you just been dependent
on cost activity and that's also like
deep down anybody everybody knows like
people that kind of and I think most
people depend on some sort of activities
to some extent and deep down they they
know that if they were to stop things
would get bad B
internally so then they just go until
they basically crash there's no stopp it
they can't stop because if they stop
then this animal just comes and stands
in front of
them and it's like
who that's what would have meant when he
said to angulimala well I I stopped you
the one still
moving he stopped any activity on
account of the pressure of the animal it
just does not exist anymore the animal
is Ted so it's completely
still and interestingly enough fimal
understood it despite all his other
it despite all his other
actions means he was probably very
acutely aware of that
pressure and that he was acting out of
that that very
thing so the light comes from the
animal the danger comes from the
animal remove moving the
Delight frees you from the
danger and that's
basically the Escape when it stops the
lighting on its own accord cuz it sees
for itself that oh yeah they would have
been to my own like they would have led
to my own
harm um that's even like that's even
freedom is out of your hands so to speak
cuz now the animal's
tamed you don't have to maintain it you
don't have to do do it you have to keep
checking in you just saw for
itself that these things are always un
beneficial like to the core and just a
inkling towards the Delight would bring
that whole weight of Terror implied in
it so again it's not like you need to
free yourself from
Delight or you you need to figure out
the
danger the animal needs to see
that so in a
way teaching that it's less less intense
let's put it that
way like if you think you need to figure
it out yourself like and I'm not seeing
it and I'm not seeing it you'll be just
just going in circles filling out with
doubt and so on and
still not really arriving
at any conclusion because there is no
conclusion to WR it doesn't pertain to
you but if you know no no no it's about
not acting out my body speech and mind
established in virtue sense
restraint non-
distraction and then just maintaining
this contexts not too much not too
little because that's what animal
sees sees your little body language when
you're not thinking about it well now
you're always thinking about it so your
little body language is the intentional
messages to the animal because you learn
oh that's the level it
reads so that's why even these
contemplations don't need to be
necessarily unpleasant it's only unpleasant if
unpleasant it's only unpleasant if
you've been giving into the delight and
then the danger of it been made visible
well then you feel the weight of that
Terror but if you don't give into the
Delight the implication is more than
enough for you to see the full extent of
it without needing to be
terrorized in that sense cu no amount of
animals Delight can make you act that's
the whole point you are the one choosing
to do
so so even if you're all filled with
confusion and doubt on some days and you
don't see the animal and this and
everything is now nothing's clear well
what's clear is what not to do by Body
speech and mind so even if I'm not
seeing the animal I know it's close cuz
I'm not giving into his pressure that's
it